Finding aid to Elizabeth Deering Hanscom papers CA.MS.01128
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth Deering Hanscom papers
1892-1971
Smith College Archives
Hanscomb, Elizabeth Deering, 1866-1960
CA.MS.01128
0.438 linear feet (1 container)
Elizabeth Deering Hanscom was a professor of English at Smith College. Her papers contain correspondence, news clippings, photographs, and publications by and about Professor Hanscom primarily regarding her professional life.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Elizabeth Deering Hanscom papers were donated to the College Archives by Elizabeth Deering Hanscom.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Deering Hanscom was born in Saco, Maine in 1866. She received a BA from Boston University in 1887, and in 1893, received an MA from the school. From 1887- 1889, she worked as a journalist. In 1894, she received a Ph.D. from Yale University, the first year that the school awarded the degree to women, and that same year she joined the Smith College faculty as a member of the English department, where she remained until 1932. In 1899, she introduced the study of American Literature to the college, which, along with 14th century English Literature, was her area of expertise. Hanscom edited and compiled American letters into two volumes, The Friendly Craft (1909), and The Heart of the Puritan (1917). Hanscom also co-wrote Sophia Smith and the Beginnings of Smith College with Helen F. Greene in 1925 for the 50th anniversary of the college. She died on February 2, 1960 in Weymouth, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains professional and personal correspondence to various recipients, photographs, news clippings about Elizabeth Deering Hanscom and copies of four of her books, including The Friendly Craft and Sophia Smith and the Beginnings of Smith College., as well as other writings.
Hanscomb, Elizabeth Deering, 1866-1960; Hanscomb, Elizabeth Deering, 1866-1960
- Professor of English (1894-1932) materials, 1916-1971 (Box 850, Folder 1)
- Correspondence – Boyd, Gertrude (Lyford), 1911, 1913-1958 (Box 850, Folder 2)
- Correspondence – Cahoon, Jean C., (1911), 1927 (Box 850, Folder 3)
- Correspondence – Emerson, Edward Waldo, 1904 (Box 850, Folder 4)
- Correspondence – Hanscom, Lizzie D. (1961), 1911 (Box 850, Folder 5)
- Correspondence – Leland, Marine, 1951-1959 (Box 850, Folder 6)
- Correspondence – Sachs, Mary (Koues), (1912), 1959 (Box 850, Folder 7)
- Correspondence – To, 1914-1953 (Box 850, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1892-1925 (Box 850, Folder 9)
- Publications, 1892-1927 (Box 850, Folder 10)
- The Heart of the Puritan, 1917 (Box 850, Folder 11)
- Sophia Smith and the Beginnings of Smith College, 1925 (Box 850, Folder 12)
- The Friendly Craft, 1909-1910 (Box 850, Folder 13-14)